Where is he?
Gdzie on jest?
Hey, you okay?
Dobrze się czujesz?
Did you just wake up?
Przysnąłeś?
Tachikawa.
Tachikawa.
Where are you going?
Dokąd idziesz?
Izumi, where do you think you're going?
Izumi, dokąd się wybierasz?
AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
You shouldn't move.
Nie ruszaj się.
It'll only hurt more if you do.
Bo będzie bardziej boleć.
WHAT MAD UNIVERSE
SZALONY WSZECHŚWIAT
PAINT THINNER
ROZCIEŃCZALNIK
Hey, look.
Spójrz tam.
Hey, are you okay?
Nic ci się nie stało?
What is this?
Co to?
Shit!
Cholera!
I morphed without thinking and some of it got inside me.
Bezmyślnie się zmieniłem i mam teraz to coś w sobie.
There was something up there, wasn't there?
Coś tam było, prawda?
Yeah. Let's check it out!
Tak. Sprawdźmy to.
That sound came from the Fine Arts room.
Dźwięk dochodził z pracowni plastycznej.
He's on the move.
- Przemieszcza się. - Dokąd idzie?
Something's not right.
Coś tu nie gra.
Is this really Shimada?
To naprawdę Shimada?
His thoughts are disjointed.
Ma mętlik w głowie.
Or rather, completely incoherent.
Nie myśli logicznie.
Hey, what was that sound?
Co to był za hałas?
I think there's something in the Fine Arts room.
Coś jest w pracowni plastycznej.
"Something"?
„Coś”?
All right. I'll go take a look.
Dobrze, sprawdzę to.
You guys go back to class.
Wracajcie na lekcję.
-No way. -Come on, sir.
- Nie. - Sensei…
I must…
Muszę…
I must restore my human appearance.
Muszę wrócić do ludzkiej postaci.
I can't. The cells on the surface are…
Nie mogę. Komórki na powierzchni…
My body is maintaining attack formation.
Moje ciało jest w pozycji atakującej.
How can I restore my human appearance?
Jak mam wrócić do ludzkiej postaci?
Wait. "Attack"?
Chwila. „Atak”?
I can't contact my cells due to interference from the dead cells.
Martwe komórki przeszkadzają mi w kontakcie z żywymi.
I have to unify my thoughts first.
Najpierw muszę pozbierać myśli.
What?
Co?
What am I doing?
Co ja robię?
Hey, what's going on?
Co tu się dzieje?
What's that you're wearing on top of your head?
Co ty masz na głowie?
What's wrong?
Co się stało?
He just killed about three of something.
Zabił trzy istoty.
Over there!
Tam!
What is he talking about?
O co mu chodzi?
Call the police!
Wezwij policję!
Okay!
Dobrze!
Where is he, Migi?
Gdzie on jest, Migi?
Wait.
Chwila.
Shimada's signal is scattered to the extreme.
Sygnał Shimady jest rozproszony.
He's moving quickly toward your classroom.
Idzie szybko w stronę twojej klasy.
What?
Co?
ART ROOM
PRACOWNIA PLASTYCZNA
I can't get through here.
Tędy nie przejdę.
Combat will be impossible in these circumstances.
W tych warunkach walka będzie niemożliwa.
For now, let's evacuate with the others.
Ewakuujmy się z resztą.
Didn't something like this happen before?
To się już wcześniej wydarzyło.
You mean Killer A?
Mówisz o zabójcy X?
What now?
A teraz to kto?
Obviously, it's Killer B.
No jasne, że zabójca Y.
What are you doing?
Co robicie?
Go! Now!
Idźcie! No już!
Go! Hurry!
Idźcie! Szybko!
Is Sasaki okay?
Sasaki dobrze się czuje?
He looks more dangerous than whatever's going on.
Chyba trochę przesadza.
Students are to go home immediately once you
Uczniowie mają iść do domu,
But what about our belongings?
A nasze rzeczy?
Get them tomorrow, okay?
Weźmiecie je jutro.
Oh, Vice Principal.
Panie wicedyrektorze.
-None of the Class 3-3 students are here. -What?
- Nie ma tu klasy 3-3. - Słucham?
That's Murano's class.
To klasa Murano.
Aren't the police here yet?
Policji jeszcze nie ma?
Now that you mention it, they are rather late.
Coś się spóźniają.
Migi, what is Shimada's position?
Migi, gdzie jest Shimada?
Are we going to fight him, then?
Będziemy z nim walczyć?
I'm more worried about Murano's class right now!
Martwię się bardziej o klasę Murano.
Shinichi!
Shinichi!
It's Class 3-3!
To klasa 3-3!
I don't see her.
Nie widzę jej.
Don't tell me. Murano.
Chyba nie… Murano…
Sorry, I mistook you for someone else.
Przepraszam, pomyliłam cię z kimś.
Was that our last conversation?
To była nasza ostatnia rozmowa?
No way.
Nie wierzę.
I can't accept that.
Nie pogodzę się z tym.
Shimada's on the third floor.
Shimada jest na trzecim piętrze.
Calm down, Shinichi!
Shinichi, uspokój się!
Shinichi, control your breathing!
Shinichi, zapanuj nad oddechem.
What have I…
Co ja…
What have I been doing all this time?
Co ja robiłem przez ten czas?
I'm breaking.
Rozpadam się.
My heart's breaking.
Moje serce się rozpada.
It's about to split in two.
Rozpadnie się na pół.
You're fine.
Nic ci nie jest.
You should be fine.
Wszystko z tobą w porządku.
I can't…
Nie mogę…
I can't do this anymore.
Nie dam już rady.
Izumi-kun, you've changed.
Izumi-kun, zmieniłeś się.
Are you made of steel?
Jesteś ze stali?
Steel?
Ze stali?
Have you calmed down?
Uspokoiłeś się?
Yeah.
Tak.
I'm going to protect Murano.
Będę chronić Murano.
To do that, I will kill him.
Dlatego muszę go zabić.
Sorry, I mistook you for someone else.
Przepraszam, pomyliłem cię z kimś.
Migi, how far are we from Shimada?
Migi, jak daleko jest Shimada?
About 60 meters.
Jakieś 60 metrów.
He's on this floor.
Jest na tym piętrze.
There are two people far away
Dwie osoby są daleko,
and three relatively close by.
a trzy dość blisko.
And one "animal".
I jedno „zwierzę”.
You have excellent hearing.
Masz świetny słuch.
EXIT
WYJŚCIE
It's coming from over there.
Słychać ich tam.
Are you okay?
Nic wam nie jest?
Are you hurt?
Jesteście ranni?
Murano.
Murano.
It's okay now!
Już dobrze! Wszystko będzie dobrze.
-Where did you come from? -Can you get up?
- Skąd się tu wziąłeś? - Możesz wstać?
I guess not.
Chyba nie.
All right. Let's go together.
Chodźmy razem.
Go where?
Dokąd?
I came from over that way.
Przyszedłem stamtąd.
Let's go back there.
Pójdźmy tamtędy.
What?
Co?
But that's where…
Ale to tam…
That's where everyone's dead.
Tam wszyscy zginęli!
Right now, it's safe.
To bezpieczna droga.
He's not there.
Nie ma go tam.
No way!
Nie wierzę!
You said you came from over there, right?
Przyszedłeś stamtąd, tak?
Are you human?
Jesteś człowiekiem?
Don't! Come back!
Nie! Wracajcie!
He's right there.
Jest tam.
This is his true nature!
To jego prawdziwa twarz!
He said they were looking for ways to coexist with humans,
Mówił, że chce koegzystować z ludźmi,
but in the end, all he can think about is killing them!
ale potrafi ich tylko zabijać!
He's coming!
Idzie!
It's okay!
Spokojnie!
I'm going to jump one more time!
Skoczę jeszcze jeden raz!
It should be safe here.
Tu będziemy bezpieczni.
Izumi-kun, I…
Izumi-kun, ja…
I know.
Wiem.
Anyone would panic when something this messed up happens.
Wszyscy spanikowaliby w takiej sytuacji.
I'm fine.
Mnie nic nie jest.
Please take care of her.
Zajmijcie się nią.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
You'll be safe now.
Teraz będziesz bezpieczna.
There's something I have to do.
Muszę coś zrobić.
We can't go in now.
Teraz tam nie wejdziemy.
You still want to fight him?
Nadal chcesz z nim walczyć?
We knew what Shimada was yet we did nothing and left him alone.
Wiedzieliśmy, kim jest Shimada, ale nic z tym nie zrobiliśmy.
I think we're partly responsible for this.
To po części nasza wina.
I guess I'm saying we're responsible for ending it.
My musimy go zabić.
You're saying peculiar things again.
Znów mówisz dziwne rzeczy.
Let the police handle this.
Niech policja się tym zajmie.
Under the circumstances, they will win.
Jest w takim stanie, że z nim wygrają.
Don't move!
Stać!
This is the police!
Policja!
Dammit! You monster!
Przeklęty potworze!
They're shooting at him.
Strzelają.
He won't die from a few small rounds.
Nie zginie od kilku strzałów.
They'll need to decapitate him or destroy his heart.
Muszą obciąć mu głowę albo zniszczyć jego serce.
Still, if injured enough, he will eventually succumb.
Ale jeśli będzie ciężko ranny, w końcu się podda.
He's heading to the roof?
Idzie na dach?
All right. But don't approach him carelessly.
Dobrze. Ale nie działajcie lekkomyślnie.
Migi, do you think Shimada is at fault?
Migi, to wina Shimady?
"Fault"?
„Wina”?
That is for humans to decide with their arbitrary metrics.
Ludzie subiektywnie wyciągną z tego taki wniosek.
I think we should finish this.
Musimy go zabić.
How?
Jak?
With this.
Tym.
But we will need to keep a distance of at least 300 meters
Musimy utrzymywać dystans co najmniej 300 metrów,
or Shimada will sense us.
bo inaczej Shimada nas wyczuje.
Yeah.
Jasne.
Shimada, this isn't just about you.
Shimada, tu nie chodzi o ciebie.
There's also Tamiya Ryoko and A.
Są też Tamiya Ryoko i X.
For what purpose did you all come into existence?
W jakim celu powstaliście?
Just add my strength to yours.
Połączmy siły.
Yeah.
Dobrze.
You know where to aim, right?
Wiesz, w co celować?
Of course.
Oczywiście.
Izumi.
Izumi.
ONE WEEK AFTER STUDENT MASSACRE NISHI FUKUYAMA HIGH SCHOOL
TYDZIEŃ PÓŹNIEJ
A week has now passed since the massacre that resulted in 17 victims.
Minął tydzień od masakry, w której zginęło 17 osób.
Circumstances surrounding the identity of the presumed killer, a student
Istnieje wiele wątpliwości wobec domniemanego sprawcy,
with a drug addiction, are suspect.
ucznia uzależnionego od narkotyków.
Police have found his identity to be forged.
Według policji posługiwał się fałszywą tożsamością.
Why are the police trying so hard to hide the truth?
Dlaczego policja chce ukryć prawdę?
They should just show Shimada's body.
Niech pokażą ciało Shimady.
Even if they did show it
Nawet jeśli je pokażą
and made it public knowledge
i powiedzą społeczeństwu,
that there exist sentient life forms who eat humans,
że istnieją stworzenia, które zjadają ludzi,
what would that accomplish?
to co im to da?
Accomplish?
Co im to da?
Well, there'd be an uproar
Ludzie się wkurzą
and calls to capture all the parasites.
i każą złapać te pasożyty.
How would they catch them?
I jak je złapią?
Humans can't do it alone.
Sami nie dadzą rady.
We'll have to cooperate with the police.
Musimy współpracować z policją.
I refuse.
Odmawiam.
Migi.
Migi.
I am my own ally.
Jestem tylko swoim sojusznikiem.
I am not an ally to the human species.
Nie jestem sojusznikiem ludzi.
I know that, but…
Wiem, ale…
Even if humans find a parasite camouflaged as a human being,
Jeśli znajdą pasożyta pod ludzką postacią,
it can assume another identity right away.
to on może przemienić się w kogoś innego.
Humans will not be able to catch them.
Ludzie nie dadzą rady ich złapać.
That's why we'll chase them down and…
Dlatego będziemy je ścigać i…
Kill them?
Zabijać?
Shinichi, I do not possess human emotions,
Shinichi, nie posiadam ludzkich emocji,
so killing my kind has no psychological effect on me.
więc zabijanie moich nie ma na mnie żadnego wpływu.
But what if you were in my position?
A gdybyś ty był na moim miejscu?
Saying this distresses him.
To go zmartwiło.
This is what humans are.
Właśnie tacy są ludzie.
Until now, we have been keeping their existence a secret to avoid panic.
Trzymaliśmy to w tajemnicy, żeby nie wywołać paniki.
However, perhaps it is now time to make it public knowledge.
Ale najwyższa pora o tym powiedzieć.
But going public will only lead to further chaos.
Ale to tylko pogłębi chaos.
There are rumors that they're trying to weaponize parasites in the U.S.
Podobno USA próbują zmienić te pasożyty w broń.
-Let's go public. -What?
Powiedzmy o nich.
And how do you intend to go about it?
Jak chce pan to zrobić?
By public,
Nie twierdzę, że mamy powiedzieć o istnieniu tych stworów,
but rather, implicitly suggesting the means of distinguishing
tylko zasugerować, jak rozróżniać
between human beings and parasites.
człowieka od pasożyta.
And how will we do that?
A jak można to zrobić?
Wait. We have a way to do that?
Chwila. Potrafimy ich rozróżniać?
I'll let Dr. Yui explain.
Doktor Yui to wyjaśni.
I'll now explain what we've uncovered so far
Powiem, co odkryliśmy
regarding the parasite's physiology.
w kwestii fizjologii pasożytów.
This parasitic life form has the ability to serve as the human brain,
Ta pasożytnicza forma życia może służyć jako ludzki mózg,
that is, the command center of the entire body,
czyli centrum sterowania ciałem,
and to push it beyond its physiological limits.
i doprowadzać ciało poza granice wytrzymałości.
Their cells resemble neurons
Ich komórki przypominają neurony,
but could be characterized as sentient muscle.
ale można je określić jako mięsień czujący.
"Sentient muscle".
„Mięsień czujący”?
However, they are capable of much more.
Ale potrafią dużo więcej.
They can morph in an instant
Mogą się przemieniać,
to stretch like rubber or become as hard as steel.
rozciągać jak guma albo być twarde jak stal.
Then, how can such an alien cell type form connections with the human body?
A jak ich komórki łączą się z ludzkim ciałem?
That is accomplished by instantaneous fusion between the two cell types.
Przez fuzję dwóch rodzajów komórek.
It's likely made possible by compounds similar to polyethylene glycols,
To możliwe dzięki związkom podobnym do glikoli polietylenowych…
please tell us how to tell them apart first.
Jak je odróżnić?
What?
Słucham?
So…
Proszę.
Although they are sentient muscle, when enough of their cells assemble,
Mimo że są mięśniem,
they possess intelligence on par with that of humans.
ich inteligencja będzie równa ludzkiej.
But if there aren't enough, what do you think happens?
Ale co się stanie, jeśli będzie ich za mało?
If they cannot secure blood circulation, they shrivel up and die,
Bez krążenia krwi kurczą się i umierają,
so they try to fuse with other cells of their kind.
więc chcą łączyć się z komórkami swojego gatunku.
Should they become a fragment about the size of a hair,
Jeśli mały fragment odłączy się,
they may writhe out of survival instinct,
będzie próbował przetrwać,
but they are too small
ale brak mu inteligencji, żeby spróbować się przyłączyć.
When you pull out human hair, nothing happens,
Jeśli wyrwiemy włos człowiekowi, nic się nie stanie,
but if you pull out hair from a camouflaged parasite,
ale jeśli wyrwiemy go pasożytowi, będzie się skręcał przez kilka sekund,
before the cells separate and die.
zanim komórki rozdzielą się i umrą.
In other words,
Innymi słowy,
pulling out a strand of hair is one way to identify a parasite.
możemy odróżnić pasożyta od człowieka, wyrywając mu włos.
Well done, Professor.
Brawo, profesorze.
But what if they wear wigs?
A jeśli noszą peruki?
If you harbor any suspicions,
Można wtedy wyrwać włos z brwi albo nawet z nosa.
The idea is to isolate a hair-sized mass from the main body.
Chodzi o to, żeby oderwać jakiś fragment.
I see.
Rozumiem.
If that's the case…
W takim razie…
Now, I do apologize for the intrusion, but before you all leave this room,
Przepraszam za niedogodność, ale zanim wyjdziecie z sali,
I ask that you allow me to pull out a strand of your hair.
chciałbym wyrwać każdemu włos.
Huh?
Co?
Although the possibility that one of them is among us is low,
Prawdopodobieństwo jest małe, ale może być wśród nas jeden z nich.
After a time, our school reopened.
Po jakimś czasie otworzyli szkołę.
Murano.
Murano.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
Are you doing okay now?
Już wszystko w porządku?
Yeah.
Tak.
I'm sorry I didn't respond to your messages.
Przepraszam, że nie odpowiadałam na twoje wiadomości.
It's okay.
Nie szkodzi.
Shall we go?
Idziemy?
Yeah.
Tak.
How is Tachikawa?
Jak się ma Tachikawa?
Yuko's better, too.
Yuko czuje się lepiej.
-She said she'll come to school today. -I see.
- Dziś przyjdzie do szkoły. - Rozumiem.
It sounded like she had a hell of a scare.
Chyba bardzo się wystraszyła.
She's always been a strong person.
Zawsze była silna.
Yeah.
Tak.
I've been wanting to thank you.
Chcę ci podziękować.
If you hadn't been there…
Gdyby cię tam nie było…
It's all in the past.
To już przeszłość.
Let's try to think of other things.
Nie myślmy o tym.
Okay.
Dobrze.
But are you okay?
A tobie nic nie jest?
You jumped down from pretty far up.
Skoczyłeś z wysoka.
Yeah, I guess it was an adrenaline rush or something.
Tak, to chyba przez adrenalinę.
I'm surprised myself.
Sam jestem w szoku.
I see.
Rozumiem.
But I really mean it.
Naprawdę bardzo ci dziękuję.
Sure.
Nie ma sprawy.
-Morning!
- Cześć!
In the end, the government did not make a public announcement
Ostatecznie rząd nie poinformował ludzi
about the parasites' existence.
o istnieniu pasożytów.
But a fad began in which
Ale powstała nowa moda.
people would greet each other by pulling out each other's hair.
Teraz ludzie na powitanie wyrywają sobie włos z głowy.
Next time, "The Blue Bird."
Kolejny odcinek: „Niebieski ptak”.